Have you applied for a term policy? Your income is 3 lakhs, but
to purchase that policy, the minimum income required was 5 lakhs. Still you
got a term policy. To purchase that policy, the minimum education
required was graduate and you are 10th or 12th pass, still you got the policy. And you
do not even know that your policy shows you as a graduate and income of 7 lakhs.
I am not talking about just one company. If you
purchase a policy of any company, you must check back in your policy bond whether the information
you have given is the same as the information that has come in your policy bond because if
there is a mistake in the information, your claim will be rejected. Your family will suffer
. If there is a mismatch in your information, then email the company.
Write in the email that my income is 3 lakhs and is my education 10th or 12th pass
? This is the name of the policy I purchased. This is the policy number.
Tomorrow if there is an early claim or a later claim, will my family get the claim or
not? Take a print out of whatever return comes and
attach it with the policy bond so that in future your nominee and your family
do not face any problem at the time of claim. And if you check this policy bond while purchasing the policy,
you will have a grace period of 1 month. At that time, if there
is any mismatch or the policy has been sold to you in a wrong way, then you
will be able to take a free look at the policy and can also get the entire money back in case of fraud or misselling
and if you take a free look even after the policy is issued, then
after paying some small charges, you will get the policy back. But if you do misselling, then it
is possible that you may get 100% money even after the issue and it is possible that you
can avoid the claim being rejected. From buying the policy to getting the policy bond at home,
do check it once. It is your responsibility because whatever you have mentioned
is coming in your policy bond. Is there any communication gap?
Is there any spelling error? Is there any error in the address? Is there any error in the mobile number or email
? Has the nominee's details been filled up correctly or not?
Did you receive the benefit illustration that was told to you or not? Hello friends, my name
is Anil Rajpurohit. I am the founder of First Financial Services, an MBA in Finance and
have been working in the corporate sector for 15 years. And today I
am presenting to you understanding the policy bond of HDFC Life Insurance in detail,
understanding the proposal form in detail, understanding the benefit illustration and
where will you find all the benefits and details and all the information about your policy? If a claim comes, a natural claim
comes, then how will the claim be made? How can you make an accidental claim
and if you have to make a complaint, whom should you do it to, on which number can you talk
? Who can you email? I have given all the details in this video.
Earlier, I have also explained the policy bond of Tata AIa in detail. You can also watch that video
on my channel. In future , I will explain
the policy bonds of other companies in detail. Here I
am explaining the proposal form and policy bond of the Term Plus Uli Plan. All other plans similar to this,
whether it is a term plan or a ULIP plan or traditional policies or
plans with bonus, the policy bond and their information are given in the same way.
Watch this video completely. If you find the video helpful, then
do not forget to like, share and subscribe to my YouTube channel Anil Raj Triple FS. Thank you. Today we will understand
the policy bond of HDFC Life Insurance's Term Plus Uli Plan. Whichever policy you
purchase. Whether it is a guaranteed policy, bonus based policy, term
policy, term plus up, pension plan, you
will get the policy bond in this way. I will explain in detail what details will be there in the policy bond
. This is a 108 page policy bond. So
I will explain in detail all the pages. So the video will become very long.
I will try to explain the important points for you here. On the first page you
will get your basic details. You will get the name of the plan etc. here. Now
what is most important for you? I will start from that page first. Then
I will come to all the other things as well. If you go to page number 68 where your proposal form is there,
you must check the details that you have filled while purchasing the policy once
because if there is a mismatch in the details then your claim can also be rejected. Now
Like here you will find your name, date of birth, your education, like
graduate is written here in education. Now many times it happens that customers also to get a policy,
let's say he is 12th pass or secondary or he has started going to college. He
had not completed graduation but declared himself as a graduate so that he can get the policy
. Many times someone's education is only 10th pass but to get a policy,
he shows his education as higher. Many times the income is less but if the income
is shown as more then the income waiver comes and the policy is available. So many times
the customer also does this. Many times the advisor can also do this for you. So
once the policy bond comes to your home, then definitely check whether the details you have mentioned
are the same or not. If it is different then it is possible that your claim may be rejected in the future
because they assume that you are taking a pure term policy.
It is necessary to be a graduate there. But if you are not a graduate but
you took the policy by showing it in the policy bond, then your claim can be rejected. Suppose to purchase the policy, it
is necessary to have an income of more than ₹ 5 lakh. And you have shown an income of ₹ 7 lakh but
the actual income is ₹ 4 lakh. Your claim can be rejected. Now you will think that when
I told you, why did the company not ask for the documents? Because when someone
is a graduate, the income is good, then many times the company makes the income void where
the company does not ask for the income document, so now this is the proposal form, this is the policy bond, this
is legally the document of the customer and the company as per the law, so whatever
you tell here, it is your responsibility that everything should be true. So whatever
you tell here, always tell the truth whether you have any illness or whatever your income is or
education, tell honestly otherwise your claim can be rejected. Now here
you will get the address proof. For example, I received a call from this customer
. In reality, his income is only ₹3.5 lakh. And the person through whom he
has purchased the policy told him that the policy was given to him by including his other income
. Whereas if you see the other income in the form below, here business, house,
property, capital gain investment, zero income is shown. Only 100%
income is shown from salary. That means he is not even eligible for this plan but
the policy has been sold to him because an income of ₹ lakh has been shown. So you should also see that
in your policy, the actual income that you have, which is in your salary slip or
the income in your ITR, is shown or something else.
Is there any problem in education? Also check your email ID etc. to see
if there is any spelling error there. Is there any mismatch in the mobile number because
all future communications are done on email. If it is on the mobile number, then you must check that too
. You must also check the address proof etc.
You must check the spelling of your name and all those things here. Apart from this,
you must also give information about the existing insurance here. Because many times it happens that let's assume that
your income is ₹5 lakh. If you are 40 years old, then you get 20 times the insurance of your income.
That means you can take insurance cover up to ₹1 crore. Suppose you already
have an insurance of 50 lakhs. You will get 50 lakhs. But now if you have not shown the existing insurance
and taken a new policy of 1 crore, then even there you
will not get the full claim of 1 crore. Because you have hidden the existing policy. So if
you already have a policy, then you should always tell the company which company's
policy it is, how much insurance cover is there. All the information should be given. Plus, if any of your
policies have had extra loading in the past or
have been postponed due to any reason, you should inform about it. If there are any health issues,
you should definitely inform the company about it. You should also check your height and weight because many times
people are overweight and get the policy passed by showing less weight in the policy
. Whereas he is overweight. So do not hide this. Check the original.
Whether your weight has been mentioned here or not.
You should definitely mention all the policy details of your previous company here.
If you have one, then definitely check the nominee details here once to see whether
their details have been filled up correctly or not. Here
you will also get to see all the information of the rest of the policy. Along with this, since this is a term plus
ULIP plan, you can also see the information of
the funds in which your investment has been made here. Now here is the benefit illustration
Check the policy you have purchased once to see if the benefit
illustration shown to you is the same as shown in your policy or if
there is any other change. Also, which funds have you invested in? If you
want to change the fund, you can do so.
You should also check the riders you have selected here. You will see here how much your total premium
is coming here. How much money will go into your investment here. How will your
charges be refunded? What charges are being deducted?
You will also get all this information. You will also get how much money you will get on maturity. Will
all the basic features be available on maturity? What is the death benefit?
What are the riders? For that, I have made a video on Smart Product Plan on a separate YouTube channel
. Do watch it because I will not explain the basic features here
. What is there in the bond here? I will tell you about the important things.
What are the basic features? You
can go to my YouTube channel Anil Raj Trifle FS and type Smart Protect Plan. You will find a video there.
I have explained all the basic features in detail. Plus you
will find a customer introduction sheet. There you will find the name of your product. Your policy number.
How much money is coming from your premium? How much is going into investment? How much
insurance cover? For how many years is the premium payment term? What is the policy term?
You will also see all these information here. What riders are you taking? You will also see them.
Grace period, free look period, glamp session. All these information will be available here.
Plus how to do the claim process? By going to which email link, you
can download the claim documents file etc. If you need any information, whom
can you call on the toll free number. Who can you email? This information
is also given in the company. Policy servicing: Let's assume that you need to change the address
or there is some mismatch in the name or address, then you need to change it, then you
can do all these things by taking the help of this link. Here you
can also get information from the company by calling. You can also email. If you want to make a complaint, then
numbers have also been given for complaint. Toll free numbers have been given and the company's email
ID will be mentioned here where you will be able to do all this.
Now I will tell you one more important thing. Like
this part will be found on page number 33, where
if the customer has any problem, then he
can also complain to IRDA, or if he wants to complain to HDFC, then their email ID and all
the information has been mentioned here. If you want to go to Observers,
then you can also go there. You will also see those details here. In which city
you are, which assessment should you go to,
if there is any issue related to claim there, you can go there. You will also get these details there
. Plus,
when you purchase the policy, you will get the unit statement. This is on page number 31 for you.
All the page numbers are written here anyway, which
details are on which page. If you look at the bottom, you will see here. So now you can see here
which plan you have purchased. What is your annual premium?
What about insurance? And which funds have you selected? Is their
NAV running?
Which funds have you taken? Is the NAV running? What is the fund value age of now? Many
people ask how much of my money has gone into investment. So from here you
can see how much of your money has gone into investment? In front of 144824,
which other funds did it go to, what is the NAV of which fund and what
are their returns in today's time, you will see all this here. Now I start from the beginning.
I try to start from the first page, here you will get the information about the plan.
You will get your details. We are looking from the beginning. Your date of birth etc., when did
you purchase the policy. Which plan option have you taken.
You will get to see all the details here in the beginning. Here you will see
how much money is deducted for stamp duty, for example ₹ 18, you felt it was stamp duty. For example,
if you get a free look before the policy is issued, then you
get the entire money back. If you get a free look after the policy is insured, then
the stamp duty money is deducted from you. If the company gets a medical test done, then you
get its money back after deduction and for the number of days the insurance is in place, let's say you have 10 days.
After that I cancelled the policy on the 11th day. For 10 days your
insurance was of 50 lakhs. If you die during that time, your family gets 50 lakhs.
So the charges till that time will be deducted from your money because it is a ULIP policy,
so your NAV would also have been registered. Now suppose at that time the market performed well and you
got a little more NV, then money will come in that way. If the NAV is less, then
money will come in that way. So if you get a free look done, then also see
how you get this benefit. What are the charges?
You must also check the nomination details here once, what is there in the nomination.
The meaning of every word written in the policy will also be explained to you
in detail. What are the charges levied in the Plus Plan? Do you
get the return of charges back? You will already get this basic information in my separate video
. But you will find all this information in detail in the policy
. Now let me tell you one more thing,
I focus on the important things. Where the supposition goes on page number 18.
Here your insurance charges, mortality charges are mentioned that suppose your
age is 26 years, then your mortality charges are very low. But suppose
your age is 53 years, then the mortality charges
are quite high. So what are the mortality charges with this age?
You will also find its details here. These are charges above ₹1000. Meaning the insurance
is of ₹1000. If your age is 40 years, then ₹2 is charged for mortality. Okay?
And anyway, whatever charges are charged here, you get back double of that
in this policy. In which funds can you invest? Which funds are available
in your policy , what percentage of money goes to equity, how much
goes to debt? All these are high risk, high return or moderate,
you get all this information in your policy bond.
If you want to see the procedure of claim, you can see on page number 23 that suppose if there
is a natural death,
on natural death you will have to give the policy bond and all the other bank details
will have to be given. Like complete policy bond will have to be given
. Details of NFT will have to be given. Original policy bond will be there. Death certificate will be there and
ID proof will be required. Now if there is no natural death, then
along with all these documents, you
will also need FIR report, police panchnama, postmortem report etc. If there is death due to accident, then
along with all these details, you will also need this police panchnama. Police inquiry report or FIR
report and or any certification from the place where you operate, that is also
required. There is the original death certification and policy bond. You have to give the complete details of all the other documents
and claim form. So what
documents are required at the time of claim, you can see here.
Here you
will find the receipt of premium payment of the first year on page number 23 27. All the page numbers are mentioned below and you have
already been told in the beginning that as you will see, first of all you are also given a table here
that what all information you will get to see in this entire policy bond.
So you can also see from here that which details you will get where
.
So here is the first receipt in which you want to take tax benefit
of ETC, then you can utilize its receipt from here.
Now let us also see a little about the exclusions in the plan that in which cases
there is no claim. If we talk about the exclusions of death benefit, if
you commit suicide and if you commit suicide before 12 months, then you will not get the benefit.
If you tell the wrong age. Suppose your actual age was 40 years but you have
given any document where the age was 38 and in that way you
have made a mistake in the calculation of your age or have hidden anything, then in that case your claim of death benefit
can be rejected or if you have hidden any pre-existing disease,
then your claim can be rejected. Now
if we talk about accidental death benefit or personal accidental cover, then in which cases your claim
can be rejected or there will be exclusions which will not be covered. In this way, we can say
that which will not be covered. We are talking about exclusions. Where there
was any pre-existing condition related to disability or
disabilities have occurred. By using alcohol or drugs etc., you have caused it
If you have any disability or accident or you
have self-injured yourself or civil war takes place etc. then if you
suffer any loss there then it will be considered in the accidental exclusion. I
am not talking about the accidental natural death cover. I
am talking about the exclusion of the coverage of the accidental rider benefit. Here,
if something happens due to viral infection or you were getting surgical treatment
for yourself and you get some disabilities there or if you are doing car racing etc. or
bungee jumping or mountain climbing, paragliding or high risk
sky driving and if you die by accident
or get disabled in all these things, then you will not get the benefits or in
this way you can see all the things here that if you
have any pre-existing problem or you are doing any such high risk thing or if there is a civil
war etc. or if something happens there or if you are doing an operation etc. and
any such incident happens at that time, then all these will come under exclusion in case of accidental.
Finally, if you have any issue, then you can also call IRDA in IRDA's grievances
. Whose number is mentioned here. You can complain. Email
ID is mentioned here. I am telling you this email ID of IRDA. Or you
can also go to Bima Bharosa or you can also complain to IRDA on this address. So
you
will get this complete proposal form in this way of 101 pages. Where
you will get all your details. Do check the details once. If you
are purchasing the policy for the family, then do inform the family members about the policy you have bought
because if they themselves do not know then who will go for the claim?
So you saw how all the details are mentioned in the proposal form.
What was your income? Do check what was your education. Do check your height and weight
. Whether your health condition has been mentioned correctly or not.
Whether the correct information of existing insurance has been given or not? Do check all those things.
If it has not been given then keep an email to the company. Whatever reply you get on the email,
do attach it to the policy bond or if you want to take a free look, you can also take a free look
. Be careful while purchasing the policy and give the correct information. You should also
tell your family members that I have purchased the policy bond or the policy has been taken for you,
then definitely inform them also and after purchasing the policy for yourself,
do open the policy bond once and see. This will be very helpful to you. If this video
has been helpful for you, then definitely subscribe to my YouTube channel Anil Rajpurohit Triple FS
and if you want to consult before buying the policy or have already
taken the policy and want to understand it, want to consult, then you
can consult me ​​on the number given below 9909403412. Thank you so much. Jai
Hind.